what is the larger cultural relevance of
cognitive science well cognitive science
is trying to fulfill the Scientific
Revolution in a very important way
there's a hole in our scientific
worldview one of the things we can't
offer a scientific explanation of is the
processes by which we generate
scientific explanations there's a
there's this hole this gap right at the
center of our scientific worldview and
cognitive science has taken upon itself
the noble enterprise the noble task of
trying to close that goal by doing
synoptic integration through these high
plausibility constructs how do we
fulfill the scientific revolution we're
going to try and offer a naturalistic
explanation of the mind we're going to
take the lessons from the previous
scientific X revolutions and use them to
try and explain the mind so what are
those three revolutions the first is in
ancient Greece at the time of sale ease
so theories did something very radical
he transformed explanations of the
worlds so I can give you a couple
fragments from what Bailey said we don't
have very much but two very famous ones
are all is the moist and the lodestone
has tsuki this is one of the first times
when the work that's in part of
psychology is used in the scientific
explanatory manner so this is important
what does this mean he means that
everything is made out of water
now he's wrong but that doesn't matter
it's not the conclusion that matters
it's the new way of thinking what he's
saying is everything's made out of water
because if I dig into the worth earth I
find water water falls from the sky
Greece is surrounded by water every
living thing seems to need water water
can take the shape of anything it's a
really plausible idea that everything is
made out of water but notice what he's
doing is he's trying to analyze complex
phenomena into more basic substances so
rather than explaining things in terms
of supernatural agents and their motives
he's analyzing things into
more basic substances what does the
loads don't have suki means the
lodestone is a natural form of magnet so
you know magnet can attract things or it
can move itself so the idea is this
originally doesn't mean mind it has a
more broad sense of right it can move
itself to have psyche to have tsuki is
you can move yourself and this is what
Bailey's is thinking he's thinking oh so
living things can move themselves and
magnets can move themselves so they must
share the same underlying basic force
sookay now he's wrong but again being
the conclusion being wrong doesn't
matter the way of thinking is really
profound he's offering a plausible
construct that right allows him to
analyze more complex phenomena into more
basic forces so here he's looking for
more basic substances here he is looking
for more basic forces so he's replaced
mythological thinking with this right
naturalistic analysis in terms of more
basic substances and forces the second
revolution right is not a revolution so
much of analysis like here it's a
revolution of formalization this is made
famous by descartes this is the idea
that we're going to get good
explanations in science when we can
offer mathematical explanation so this
is typify dry by mathematical formula
the reason why this is so important is
because this is again a really highly
plausible construct because there's a
lot of evidence that converges on this
but this is a way of representing things
look look when I talk about forces mass
times acceleration I can apply it to how
bricks are moving how rocks are moving
how apples are famously falling out of
trees right this applies to all of them
broadly but powerfully so math really
ramps this all up so you want an after
analyzing you want to try and explain
all your basic processes and forces in
mathematical terms you want to try and
formalize them and in cognitive science
a lot of the formalization it does take
place through various kinds of logical
theories mathematical theories
information processing theories the
third revolution is important because as
hacking has famously argued here at UofT
science isn't just about explaining the
world science is about intervening in
the world being able to change the world
being able to make things we believe in
science more when it allows us to change
the world to achieve the socially
relevant goals were pursuing and what
happened with Turing in the 1940s and
50s was the revolution of mechanization
Turing came up with a proposal that said
we can go from just representing to the
mind to actually intervening in reality
to creating the mind to creating
artificial intelligence we can create
machines that take the analysis take the
formalization and then give those
machines causal power we can actually
make the mind and this means that the
these kinds of computational metaphors
are again highly plausible a lot of
ideas converge on them but they were
powerfully insightful that's the whole
computer revolution so what cognitive
science is doing is it's saying I'm
gonna we're going to do synoptic
integration by creating very highly
plausible constructs that allow us to
extend this naturalistic process of
analyzing formalizing and mechanizing
but now we're going to do that with
respect to the mind and hopefully what
we can do is complete the Scientific
Revolution and fill that hole we'll be
able to offer a scientific explanation
of how our minds and brains create
scientific explanations
that's what Scoggins science is all
about
you